Guide to the Harry Turner Papers TAM.208
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harry Turner Papers
circa 1968-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Turner, Harry
TAM.208
3.75 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
Harry Turner (1919-1997), born in Brooklyn, N.Y., joined the Communist Party in the 1930s, left in the aftermath of the Soviet suppression of the Hungarian Revolution of 1956, became a Trotskyist, and was a member of the Socialist Workers Party (1964-66), then helped establish the Spartacist League, but left it in 1968, then participated in various U.S. and international Trotskyist organizations until his death. Turner was also a rehabilitation counseler, working for the New York State Office of Vocationa Rehabilitation, and an activist in the New York State Civil Service Employees Association. The collection contains published and unpublished writings by Turner -- newspaper articles, pamphlets, statements, newsletters, and circular letters -- the latter two often relating to the many Trotskyist organizations in which he participated. Materials also include correspondence, reports, newsletters, and ephemera documenting Turner's engagement with various Trotkyist and socialist organizations. The Trotskyist Coordinating Committee, Collective Leadership Faction (CLF), and the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP) are particularly well documented. Other groups in the collection include the Workers Revolutionary Party (WRP), International Socialist League (ISL), International Workers League (IWL), and the International Workers Party (IWP).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
There is no documentation concerning the provenance of the original donation in this collection; the accession number associated with these materials is 1998.014. In October 2019 and March 2022, Jon Willinger donated accretions to the collection. The accession numbers associated with these accretions are 2019.124 and 2022.025, respectively.
Biographical Note
Harry Turner (1919-1997), born in Brooklyn, N.Y., joined the Communist Party in the 1930s, left in the aftermath of the Soviet suppression of the Hungarian Revolution of 1956, became a Trotskyist, and was a member of the Socialist Workers Party (1964-66), then helped establish the Spartacist League, but left it in 1968, then participated in various U.S. and international Trotskyist organizations until his death. Turner was also a rehabilitation counseler, working for the New York State Office of Vocationa Rehabilitation, and an activist in the New York State Civil Service Employees Association. A detailed listing of Turner's writings is available at the Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains published and unpublished writings by Turner -- newspaper articles, pamphlets, statements, newsletters, and circular letters -- the latter two often relating to the many Trotskyist organizations in which he participated. Materials also include correspondence, reports, newsletters, and ephemera documenting Turner's engagement with various Trotkyist and socialist organizations. The Trotskyist Coordinating Committee, Collective Leadership Faction (CLF), and the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP) are particularly well documented. Other groups in the collection include the Workers Revolutionary Party (WRP), International Socialist League (ISL), International Workers League (IWL), and the International Workers Party (IWP).
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Materials received in 2019 and 2022 are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor. The nature of the arrangement for records received prior to 2019 is unknown.
Appraisal
Personal check donations to the Trotskyist Coordinating Committee have been appraised out of this collection and destroyed.
Communism -- United States.; Socialism -- United States.; Turner, Harry; Trotskyist Organizing Committee; Revolutionary Unity League
- Published and Unpublished Writings, 1968-1990 (Box 1)
- Published and Unpublished Writings, 1973-1998 (Box 2)
- Published and Unpublished Writings, 1973-1998 (Box 3)
- Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP), 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
- Emergency National Conference (ENC), Minneapolis, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Workers Revolutionary Party (WRP), circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
- Trotskyist Coordinating Commitee, 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
- Trotskyist Conference Committee, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 8-10, Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Collective Leadership Faction (CLF) Appeal to International Workers League (IWL), 1982-1986 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
- Collective Leadership Faction (CLF) Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
- Collective Leadership Faction (CLF) -- General, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
- Gulf War, 1991-2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- International Socialist League (ISL) Correspondence, 1989-1992 (Box 7, Folder 5-10)
- International Workers League (IWL) Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
- International Workers Party (IWP), 1988 (Box 8, Folder 5-7)